good morning everybody well today we've
got a big project going on I've been
looking forward to this project for
several months and I've not been looking
forward to this project for several
months
today we're going to be
[Music]
trenching what are we trenching we're
trenching irrigation pipe from our water
well all the way out we're tying into
the
barn we're running over to the new pen
over here and then all the way down to
the new uh chicken house and we're going
to put new Waters out there so we're
looking at about 300 ft that
way then on what you can't see from this
point of view is we're tying in to the
barn for the new water for the bathroom
and the shower going around the barn
we're putting in the high tunnel
so we're going to have water out to the
high tunnel we're also going to have
water going all the way down the other
fence line all the way down to the Fig
Orchard we're putting in drip irrigation
out
there right along with me applying for
the
nrcs high tunnel grant program summer my
representative here in Escambia County
of Alabama said I'll give you money to
uh up to 1 acre of irrigation for your
or Orchard and I was like really wow and
uh so she's going to
pay the irrigation to be installed
inside the high tunnel our high tunnel
is currently on the trailer it's a 24x
60 and it's going in right there we've
got pipe going across the front of the
high tunnel and then all the way down
the long side of it and then it goes
along the fence all the way back to
where our fig Orchard is way back
there um so when she told me that I was
like well how much is the grant going to
be so for the acre and for the high
tunnel
combined um I'm only going to be out of
pocket maybe a couple hundred dollars so
all this pipe and all the drip
irrigation come to about $11,000 and so
uh when they reimburse me
I'm going to be out very little so if
you're establishing an orchard or you're
establishing an in nrcs high tunnel also
ask about the grant money to have it
irrigated and I'll see if you qualify
for that I did and I'm highly grateful
for it because I was going to end up
doing it anyway it just helps save
money everything that we do here is
going to be marketed so it's not like
I'm doing this for personal use we're
going to be selling trees plants
fruit um probably won't be going into
the fruit business for the figs for
several years we got to give those
things time to get up there um and start
producing very well all right let's go
ahead and take the trencher off and uh
let's start digging some trenching and
then putting some pipe in I've looked up
code now what you can't see from this
angle is there's two pipes laying right
here one's electrical one's for water
the big one's got my direct Berry cable
I went ahead and put it in pipe and
we're going to put all that in the
ground we're going to put it um anyc
code recommends 24 in in the ground so
we're going to put it 24 in in the
ground and uh that's that's providing
currently 100amp service to our barn so
there you can see I got my electrical
cable inside that that heavy duty inch
and a half pipe let's get you set up on
a stand and let's get this trencher off
the
[Music]
trailer
[Applause]
[Music]
a
[Applause]
[Music]
n
[Applause]
[Music]
he
all right guys that was super fast that
was 700 ft of pipe in 2 and 1/2 hours
and uh that's probably
the that was pretty it's pretty good
because last time I did any trenching I
did it with one of those that you pull
as it trenches and that thing will wear
you out I did
um probably close to 1,000 ft and it
took me 12 hours to do it and it was the
most strenuous thing I had ever
experienced my entire life I kid you not
I had every muscle in my body was sore I
had blisters all over my hands I
couldn't even use my hands for several
days and I was like never again will I
do that that's why I went and rented
this thing I rented this at my local Ace
Hardware bance and Sentry and uh I think
it's 175 a day man this thing is a
Cadillac it'll just it'll go right to
town so I got my spet down here we're
going to end up putting all the pipe in
the ground covering it up hopefully
we'll start covering and getting most of
it covered up today but I want to show
you the reason we put the spet down here
is this is my fig Orchard so we're going
to take the trencher and we are putting
a drip Mainline pipe down each one of
these rows off of the mainline pipe I'm
going to use qu in drip
line um that has a dripper every foot in
the tubing it's quar inch tubing I'm not
using drip tape drip tubing is what this
is and we're going to do a twoot ring
around each plant but I got to put down
the mainline because we have grass in
between all of our Rose still we got to
be able to cut over that with a lawn
more so I'm just going to use the
trencher just to cut myself a little
trench just shallow enough to that that
that drip line that main line will go
flat even with the ground whatever dirt
we can we put back over it and let the
grass grow back over it and we will
start putting our drip lines in as soon
as we can it probably won't be today um
because we've got so much stuff to cover
up that we've
dug all right let's get to
[Music]
it
hush hush
pyro stop it
now all right I got to the end of my
Orchard and I got my beehive down here
and the bees really didn't like the
sound of the trencher coming by and the
vibrating of the ground so I had to go
get my be suit on and we're going to go
ahead and finish up this whole end of
the orchard so I can take this beit off
CU this thing will get hot even though
it's the breathable material that's full
of holes uh it gets warm if you're
staying it very very long so we're gonna
go ahead and pick back up where we
[Music]
started
[Applause]
n
all right got the Fig Orchard done now
we're getting ready to start this row of
apples next over will be another row of
apples a row of paars and then I have a
fourth row over here that is our Arbor
which is grapes and Kiwis and stuff like
that so um finish
trenching all right earlier today we
laid our PVC pipe down this fence row so
that we can order water the animals that
are going to be in that pen um if you
look right here I got some potted plants
I've got some plants in ground down
there those are
mulberries and I've got some blueberries
I've recently bought and some uh
pineapple guava and we're going to be
running drip irrigation right down
through here and
uh so we got some plans to grow some big
fruit trees up over this pen so the
fruit drops in there for the
animals we're going to be running drip
line all the way down our
Apple our
pear our grape Vines and kiwi
Vines and along the back back there is
our fig Orchard we're going to be
running irrigation to every fig that's
in that Orchard and all total we're
looking at 3,000 ft of drip
irrigation if you are looking for a
house
to this is it this is what I'm going to
show you what I'm doing to water every
one of these uh plants on a timed drip
irrigation system with the ability to
inject
fertilizer all right want to start off
at the very head of the whole irrigation
project we have this whale here it's a
60ft whale we have a water table of
about 10 ft this well was already here
whenever we bought the place and I don't
know exactly what it was used for maybe
to water the uh pecan Orchard that's
already established here pecan trees is
about 40 years old but this doesn't tie
into anything else just irrigation I've
never had this tested so I've never
drank from this water anyway coming out
of the well pump here is a 1-in
connector now up until recently
everything was plumbed 3/4 in pipe and
that's just fine if if you're just going
to run it a short distance and uh just
do some irrigation there was nothing
wrong with that I was completely
happy our fig Orchard is 500 ft from the
beginning of this whale head to where we
have to run it over to the fence and all
the way down the fence we're looking at
500 ft in One
Direction my concern was with 3/4 in
pipe if we contined 3/4 in all the way
out to the end of the orchard I looked
up the uh the am amount of pressure loss
and I was really concerned that I
wouldn't have enough pressure at the end
of my faucet down there to properly
irrigate water through all those
emitters that I'm going to be using so
I've decided one day when uh all my
other projects were sidelined I flipped
this tank over disconnected it and I
replumbed everything here to one in pipe
I looked at the loss of before I did all
that I looked at the loss of pressure on
one inch pipe to 500 feet all the way at
the end of The Orchard and I was only
going to lose about a pound and a half
of pressure that's that's great I can I
feel really good about that um it's a
little more expensive to run 1 in pipe
500 ft versus 3/4 in pipe so I went back
to the tables and I love to see where my
greatest amount of pressure loss was at
so I ended up running 1in pipe off the
well out to my barn and then out to the
greenhouse is all one inch from the
greenhouse out to the end of my fig
Orchard is another 200 and something
feet and so with all that calcul
calculated in I was only losing just a
pound or two of pressure so I'm happy
with that that's a good compromise I
don't have to run one inch all the way
out to the orchard to get proper
pressure so I wanted to show show that
with you now I went to drip Depot and
ordered all my Irrigation Supplies I
looked between two or three popular
sites did price comparisons and I spent
about $1,000 on this irrigation system
this irrigation system is also partially
funded by a USDA Grant when I had my
Greenhouse um when I applied for my high
tunnel application summer the lady I was
working with at nrcs said hey we'll pay
for your irrigation up to one acre also
I was like great and so she put it in a
contract to how
much um money she was going to give me
on one acre and it just about pays for
the entire irrigation pipe uh tubing and
everything and so that's why I'm doing
this and I spare no expense because
everything that I'm spending is going to
be uh well worth the
price because I have 1 in pipe here I've
got some really delicate emitters that
are just drip emitters running on
quarter inch drip line they have a
tendency where they can get clogged up
really easy so I've got a
08 millimeter which is an 80 micron
filter on a 1in pipe and I didn't have
this when I replumbed it so this
downpipe goes to everything irrigation
so I'm going to come in and I'm going to
have to replum this and put a filter
here so I want to filter out everything
that's on the other side of this pipe
everything that goes over here is going
to help uh feed water to this future
apartment when we get this converted and
uh I may end up having to put another
filter on to filter that or re rewire
something but that's for me to figure
out later down the
road all right now from here
we had to trench water out to our barn
and we also had to trench uh Power from
our electrical box all the way out to
the distribution panel out at the barn
so we went ahead and laid the water pipe
right in with the uh heavy duty power
cables and we just put the both pipes in
the same hole so this pipe is twoot deep
in the ground we don't have a frost
layer here so that's not a concern for
us and everything that you see going out
in the orchard is only going to be a few
inches deep and that's only a few inches
because like I said we don't have a
freeze line here in Southern Alabama so
no reason to bury at a certain amount of
depth in order to protect those pipes we
get a couple freezing days throughout
the year and I turn this well off flip
that valve so I don't lose water down my
uh go back down into the well and lose
Prime and then I drain all my exposed
pipes that I've got so they don't bust
but we only get uh a few hours or a day
or two a year that it gets freezing and
really have to worry about doing that
but our ground never freezes all right
now let's head on out and let's show you
all the uh the components that I bought
and how we are doing our irrigation I
think it's something that you could
probably implement that you could pick
up some tips and uh Implement in your
orchard if this is the reason you're
watching this video is learn how to do
it at home
orer all right we're getting ready to
run some Mainline tubing down our fig
rows we're going to go down one row
connect over to the end and come back
the other side on another row I've got
some leftover distribution tubing here
from the previous uh two runs that we
did I've got a new roll on the back and
I'm going to show you a neat way for us
to roll this out rather than grabbing a
whole tht roll of tubing and going down
and unrolling it manually we're going to
use the back of the golf cart and
something as simple as a shovel handle
and we're going to spool it off so let
me go ahead I've got the distribution
pipe over here ready for a hose in
connector to go on it we're going to lay
it in the outfeed trench to go over to
the row and let's get busy laying out
the uh distribution pipe
now I've got a t connector I'm going to
connect or short run of this pipe and
then eventually we're going to have to
use a coupling to connect to the new
roller
[Music]
pipe
n
[Music]
all right now that we got our leftover
distrib or Mainline tubing rolled out we
at the end of the first row I've got
this thot roll loaded so we just shove a
uh shovel handle through there we're
just going to roll it off the back of
the golf cart um first I got to put a
connector to connect these tubings so
just get you a half inch connector and
just push push the ends
[Music]
together if you find out that it's a
little too hard to try to push these end
pieces
together get your little propane torch
and just wave it over the ends just to
heat them up don't sit there and melt
the plastic but just give it a little
heat and it'll go in a lot easier
so wave it over the end wave it over
that end bottom side bottom
side little more
heat there we go let see how much easier
that goes on right there that's the
secret and then this end we'll just wave
right the end of
it right over the
Heat and it goes right on a lot
[Music]
easier
all right the very first thing we're
going to do now that we've laid our um
Mainline pipe is we've got to put a hose
in on it now I went with eartech because
I like the way they fasten now this one
will Spin and lock right down on the
tubing after you put that tubing on
there you spin this and it'll lock right
down on it and create a good seal there
are some cheaper manufacturers out there
and the price is cheaper also but go
with quality if this is going to be out
here for years you don't need your
fittings blowing apart uh get something
that locks
down now I have my distribution or my
Mainline pipe right here at
my uh hose bib I've got a
fourway timer that I'm going to screw
onto here um and then all four of my
distribution lines are going to uh be
screwed onto their own um timed
irrigation
now let me get this over where I can
show you
guys this is the one we just
laid and and it's a little rough to put
on there like that
easily does not
go right on it it takes a lot of effort
to get that squeezed onto there so if
you again if you just heat the pipe up
it goes on a lot easier so I get my
propane
torch and just wave it over a couple
times loosen that pipe
up
now it's wanting to go on there now see
we didn't melt that pipe we got it loose
enough
that we got it loose enough that we can
get that started so now it's flared on
the
end wait for that to cool off cuz it's
weak right here now because I got it
warmed
up and that'll go on a lot
easier
okay now that we have on there I just
screw that down and that locks that
right into place and I'll just leave
this here the next thing that we're
going to do is we're going to go to each
plant and start putting a drip ring
around it so let's go over there and
explain that to you because we're using
drip line the drip line requires uh 25
lb or no more than 15 lbs of pressure so
for each hose in and you could put this
before the Irrigation Timer screw that
right onto
the um your hose bib and then put your
timer on this end and then put your four
distribution lines your main lines onto
your water but 15 lbs so I got a few of
those because I've got more than just
the one hose bib I've got one for the
one for the uh the trellis stuff my
grapes and I've got one over at my
mulberries and blueberries so I needed
several of
these
um I've got little quinch
couplings qu inch uh tubing I've
actually had to buy three or four rolls
of the 100t tubing because at each plant
I've got a little over foot section
that's going to tie together the uh qu
in drip line and into the uh Mainline
tubing I've got a a punch that punches a
hole into our main
line and I
ordered several hundred of these
three-way connectors and this is going
to also um connect our hoops at each
plant and I'll show you all this in a
second I bought one of these
tools and this
tool take a coupler put it in there and
it helps you put that little coupler
right onto the distribution homes a
little bit easier we'll demonstrate all
this to you in a little
[Music]
bit
n
[Music]
okay I'm going to show you how I made
the
loops take a qu
inch T
connector and I found out because I've
been hurting the ends of my fingers
getting this distribution hose pressed
onto the connector it really been
tearing my fingertips up so this morning
I figured if I take my torch and I just
put it on
low and just have a little
flame I could heat up the
end and then it slides the T connector
right onto the end of my distribution
hose right there grab this and I count
out eight of the drippers that's the
size of the hoop that I'm happy with
like I said it's about a twoot hoop
so one two 3 4 5 6 7 8 and then we're
going to cut right between the next
dripper now to make sure this ends up to
be a good size hoop stretch it straight
out so the bow is consistent bring it
back together one War the end of your
pipe
up and then put the connector on and
that
leaves the end of the connector sticking
out right there so I can put my
distribution tubing onto
that I went out into the Orchard and I
measured the distance from my Mainline
tubing over to where
my um drip tubing needs to lay and I've
got about 16
in from the two
points so this is what I had left of the
distribution tubing that I
ordered and I just come over about 16 in
I had it measured out so I know about
what that looks like and I'm just going
to cut
that
there I'm going to
take one
in and just run it over my
Flame
and then that slides right onto my
distribution
tubing onto my drip line
connector and if it's a little tough to
put on just run it over the heat one
quick
time until it's just just right you'll
figure out after one or two how long you
need to hold it over that flame but it's
probably less than a second to get it
warmed up enough you definitely don't
want to melt that so that ends up
compromising the
Integrity of the uh
joint so we got our distribution line
out here we going wave that over the
pipe real quick less than a second and
then we take our
coupling and just press it right into
our tubing and then we don't have to
tear our fingers up because we're using
our FL flame okay one of the little
things I want to show you is using this
tool now I just showed you the using the
propane torch to heat the end of the up
so that you could put these little
couplers on but if you buy the tool and
you don't want to use the
propane then the little coupler goes
right into
the uh mouth of
that and it kind of holds
it and it holds it in place then you
take your tubing and you kind of get it
started on the
end of the
coupling and then you can squeeze
that and then it puts the little coupler
on there for you nice and easy you don't
have to worry about using the propane
torch um I guess we'll see which one's
actually quicker seems like this would
be a little bit quicker and I may just
stick with doing this but I don't have a
little device to put it on the end of
that and that's the part that was
tearing the end of my fingers up is uh
putting all that together so I will keep
using the propane on this end for
sure
okay okay so this is the very first one
that I did just to make sure I had
everything down right before I brought
you guys along and showed you what I was
doing this is the very first coupler I
put on the mainline
tubing I got it in a little trim
and that trench is about 4 in deep and
that's going to go right out to that
Loop I've got a three-way connector here
Tech of course and it ties our Loop in
together that one goes down that row of
our
figs and this one goes down that row of
the
figs all right so every one of my trees
and the Fig Orchard
and the rest of my Orchard is going to
get this exact same treatment all right
so that's our main line in the ground
right there I took quarter
inch
coupler about a foot of quinch drip um
distribution
line over to our quarter inch drip line
so there's an emitter there and about a
foot apart is another emitter and
another emitter
another mitter here here here and here
decide to measure it out eight emitters
in a loop and I'm using that t connector
right there to connect it all together
so I was sitting in the house the other
night getting everything prepared and I
put this Loop together on a t connector
but and then this morning when I woke up
I went out to the barn and started
hooking in this section so
um the emitter tubing that I'm using is3
Gall per emitter per hour so it's a slow
drip now I'm going to turn it on in a
little bit and I'm going to demonstrate
to you how fast or how slow that drip
is um so that's all it is to it I've got
my fig tree here that's trimmed back
from the winter I rate back all my hay
and I put my
emitters on the ground
because I'm going to come back and cover
it back up with hay Mulch and stuff like
that and all this um hay that I'm going
to put over is going to protect it from
the Sun and it's going to protect it
from the mower and that's the reason I'm
putting the distribution and everything
in the ground and then covering this up
with mulch is to protect it all from
Sun Well weather in general and from the
mower so turn my water on let's give it
a test run and I'm going to turn this
one all the way got a 15
lb right there there's the hoop that I
just was showing
you you can see how
fast that's coming out of
there hold this up a little
bit you can
see see it dripping
all right like I previously stated in
the previous segments that we have got a
pressure reducer at the top of this
there's an inline filter and I put my
inline filter because I ordered a inline
filter with a 1 in for a 1 in pipe this
happens to be 3/4 so the filter that we
selected won't fit here without some
adapters so it's upline so we have 15 lb
reducer I've got my four Zone uh timer
it's going to be set up I haven't
selected what my watering schedule's
going to be just yet that'll be for a
later video so each one of these pipes
goes to a different zone now on my zone
like previously stated also is they're
set up on a loop water goes down hits a
three-way connector and it goes down uh
two pipes and it works on a loop system
solely for the reason of keeping
constant pressure the best that it can
so far I'm very happy with this system
and if there's anything that you
recommend or if there's anything that
this video has helped you out on please
let me know in the comments below like
subscribe and share hope you enjoyed it
remember keep growing keep building and
always keep a venturing together or
flomington famous we'll see you the next
[Music]
one